Guide to the Harold Bauer collection ARCH171
University of Hartford Archives & Special Collections
Harold Bauer collection
1900-1956
1928-1951
University of Hartford Archives & Special Collections
ARCH171
0.71 Linear Feet (3 containers)
The collection consists primarily of correspondence from Harold Bauer to Moshe Paranov from 1928-1951, as well as photographs of Harold Bauer and his master classes. The collection also includes some newspaper clippings, press releases, concert programs, and other papers.
Conditions Governing Access
The collection is open to all researchers.
Existence and Location of Copies
The correspondence in the collection has been digitized and can be accessed at: http://mdid3.hartford.edu. Access to the digital repository is limited to the University of Hartford Campus.
Biographical / Historical
Harold Bauer, world renowned concert pianist, was a long-time teacher and supporter of the Hartt School, He was closely associated with its early development and founders.
Other Finding Aids
An incomplete general index (arch1710461) and subject index (arch1710462) to the correspondence in the collection (which includes summaries of letters), can be found in the digital repository by their identifiers at: http://mdid3.hartford.edu. Public access to the digital repository is limited to the University of Hartford Campus. Students, faculty, and staff can login anywhere with their university email and password.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists primarily of correspondence and photographs from 1900-1956, with the bulk of the collection dating from 1928-1951. The correspondence is mostly between Harold Bauer and Moshe Paranov. The photographs are primarily portraits and group photographs of his master classes, but also includes a few photographs of Bauer with members of the Julius Hartt School of Music.
Related Materials
Paranov Collection
Correspondence; Music Instruction and study; Photographs; Sheet music; Bauer, Harold, 1873-1951; Paranov, Moshe, 1895-1994; Julius Hartt Musical Foundation Inc.; Julius Hartt School of Music
- Corresondence, 1928 - 1951, undated (Box 1, Folder 1 - 26)
- Photographs, 1900 - 1947, undated (Box 1, Folder 27)
  Existence and Location of Copies
  All of the photographs in the collection have been digitized and can be accessed at: http://mdid3.hartford.edu. Public access to the digital repository is limited to the University of Hartford Campus. Computers are available to the public at the Harrison Libraries. Off-campus access is available for University of Hartford students, faculty, and staff with their university email and password.
- Concert Programs, 1928 - 1956 (Box 2, Folder 2 - 3)
- Newsclips, 1951, undated (Box 2, Folder 4 - 6)
- Press Book and Press Releases, undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Publications, 1924 - 1928 (Box 2, Folder 8, Box Shared Book Tray 2, Object 0207303175500)
  Scope and Contents
  Includes copies of:
  Bauer, Harold. Harold Bauer, His Book. New York: W.W. Norton and Company, 1948.
  Bauer, Harold. The Pianist's Warming Up Excersises. New York: G. Schirmer, Inc., 1950.
  Photocopy of CD album liner notes to Harold Bauer: The 1924-28 Victor Recordings.
- Memorial Concert and Tree, 1951 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Master Class, 1933, 1941 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Teacher at Hartt, 1947 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Writings, undated (Box 2, Folder 12)